Hey, what's up guys? My name is the
channel and welcome back to my C++
series. So, today building off of what
we talked about last time with function
pointers, if you haven't seen that
video, definitely click up there to
check it out. Today we're going to be
talking talking about lambdas, and
lambdas are essentially a way to a way
for us to define something that I like
to call an anonymous function. So,
basically it's a way for us to create a
function without actually having to
physically create a function. Just like
a quick disposable function if we want
if we want to demonstrate some kind of
code that needs to be run, but we we
want to treat it more like a variable
and less than an actual formal function
that exists as like a symbol in our
actual compiled code, if that makes
sense. And obviously, when we jump into
some examples, if that didn't make
sense, hopefully that'll clear it up.
Okay, so first of all, a lambda, right?
What is it used for?
It's one thing to understand what it is,
but it's obviously a completely
different thing to understand how to use
it and when to use it. And the answer to
that is essentially whenever you have a
function pointer, you can use a lambda
in C++. That is how that works, right?
So, a lambda is just a way for us to
literally define a function without
having to define a function. So, the
usage of a lambda therefore is wherever
we would normally set a function pointer
to a function, we can set it to a lambda
instead, right? So,
really to talk about why lambdas are
useful and where you can use them,
you need to understand where you would
use a function pointer. And we
definitely did talk about that in the
function pointers video, but when we
actually start getting into concrete
examples in C++ and in this series and
especially the game engine series where
we actually build something, that's when
you'll really see me use everything that
I described in this series. So, just
keep that in mind. This is more to be
treated as like a reference and like a
oh, I don't know what this is at all or
I don't know the syntax for this actual
thing or how it works, right? So, let's
jump in and we're going to build off of
what we covered in the function pointers
video to actually demonstrate the usage
of a lambda and the different things
that we can do with it. Okay, so this is
the code that we had from the last
video. We basically just built a little
for each function, which took in a
function pointer. And in fact, last
video I even said that we did use a
lambda. This is a lambda right over
here. We did essentially define our own
function in line with the rest of our
code that just printed out whatever
value we needed. And this function
pointer essentially defined what the
lambda actually needed to be. So, in
other words, we know that it returns
void, and we know that it takes one
parameter, which is an integer. And
that's why you see this function, as you
can see, returns nothing. It just prints
out a line of text. And then we have
this integer value parameter, which is
defined because we've said that we need
to take in an integer. And in this case,
the integer that we pass into this
function
ends up being the value that we're
currently iterating over, right? So, you
can see that literally this funk value
is actually calling this code that we've
defined here in our main function. And
that really is the usage of a lambda. It
lets us do cool things like this. One of
the biggest examples I can ever give is
we want to be able to pass in a function
to an API, so that at some point in the
future it can call that function for us.
Because we don't know
we we can't call the function now
because either it doesn't have the data
it needs or we just don't want to. We
want to kind of defer the calling of a
function. And if we want to do something
like that, then of course we need to
tell it what function to call when it
gets up to the stage of I now want to
call a function. And lambdas are just a
really good way of specifying that
function, specifying code that you want
to run sometime in the future, like we
have here with this for each, where we
actually run that code when we're
iterating over the element and when it
becomes time for us to call it with a
specific parameter, as we're doing here.
So, let's dissect the syntax of this
lambda a little bit. I'm actually going
to kind of get rid of this and assign it
to an auto variable. So, auto lambda,
we'll say, equals our lambda, and then
we'll pass in the lambda into here.
All right, cool. So, first of all, we
start off a lambda with these square
brackets. Let me make some room. We
start off this lambda with the square
brackets. What is that? Now, I will
point out, first of all, that you don't
really have to take my word for it or
this video for it, cuz sometimes videos
are a bit annoying for things like this.
You can actually go over to
cppreference.com,
as I've got it open over here, and there
is an uh there's a there's a page on
lambda expressions. You can see they
exist in C++ 11, and they've actually
got the syntax of all the things you can
do. And you can see that what it calls
the first part is the captures. And of
course, it describes everything over
here. If you go to the explanation, you
can see the captures are a
comma-separated list of zero or more
captures. cppreference.com is my
favorite C++ reference website. There
are many others, and you can use all of
them, really. They're all useful. But
this one's actually quite clear, um
refer to this often, right? I'll leave a
link to the lambda page in the
description below, but in general, if
you're not sure about something like
lambdas, oh, I wonder what goes into
that capture thing or what the possible
values are, right? If you if you're
trying to figure out stuff like that,
just look it up in the reference. Okay,
so, inside here, you can see the
captures we have a comma-separated list
of zero or more captures. So, I'll
explain what this is in a minute, but
basically, you can see that we can pass
in
like variables, essentially. A would be
captured by a copy or a value, and B is
captured by reference. Here, we can pass
in this. We can pass in just an
ampersand, which captures everything by
reference. Just an equal sign, which
captures everything by value or by copy.
And then that captures nothing. So, what
is this whole capturing thing? Well,
consider this as an example. What if we
want to put outside variables into the
instructions that are inside our lambda
function?
What happens then, right? Because
remember, what we're doing is we're
constructing a function that will then
get called later.
So, if we use variables that are outside
of that lambda, like for example,
outside of this function. So, maybe I
have an int A over here that's equal to
five. What if I use that here? What if
the part where instead of printing value
or something, I want to print A? Well,
how's that going to work? Because this
is outside. And obviously, what I'm
doing is calling this code from over
here inside this for each loop. So, how
does it have access to A? Well, there's
two ways that we can pass this A
variable around. And this is the exact
same as if we had made our own function.
We can pass it by value, or we can pass
it by reference. And that is what that
capture group is for, right? That first
that square brackets, that lets us say
how we want to pass variables in. Now,
in this case, we're not passing anything
in, which is why we're getting an error
here because well, it's an enclosing
function, and we can't pass in A. But
what we can do is we can either write
equals, which means pass everything in
by value, or we can write an ampersand
like this, which means pass everything
in by reference.
Or we can actually write individual
variables like this. So, I want to pass
A by value, or with an ampersand, A by
reference. Now, in this case, we
actually get an error when we try and
pass something in. Well, actually, if we
capture anything, whether it be by value
or by reference, we're going to get an
error over here in for each, and this is
just in this specific example, because
we're just using a raw function pointer.
If we convert this to an STD function
like we will right now,
so this is going to be, of course,
returning void, taking in one int
parameter, and we'll call it func. And
I'll include functional so that we have
access to that.
Then that's going to go away. Okay, so
what we're doing here is we're passing
everything in by value, which means it's
just going to copy the value and pass it
in. But you can also use an ampersand if
you want to capture something by
reference. So, maybe if it's like a
class or a struct that you don't want to
copy, or this lambda is actually
intended to modify the code. If you're
not sure or to modify that object or
variable, if you're not sure what I mean
by passing by reference, check out both
my video on functions. I think covers a
little bit of that, but the references
video and the pointers video is also
related to that, all that stuff. If we
go back to C++ reference, we you can
also see that we have the next step,
which is the parameters, right? So,
those are the parameters that our
function takes in. We have an optional
specifier, such as mutable, which allows
the body to modify parameters captured
by copy. That's another thing that's
kind of useful. You can see here that
we're copying the A variable, but if we
try to assign A to something like that,
it's not going to let us, which is a bit
weird because we're just passing it by
value. And of course, if we were passing
something into a normal function by
value, of course we can we can reassign
it and do whatever we want. And to fix
that, you basically just add the word
mutable here. It's a bit weird, but hey,
stuff like that you probably wouldn't
even realize exists if you don't look at
things like the reference and see what's
possible because you can see that over
here, we have our kind of parameters and
whatever, which is one of them is that
that beautiful optional kind of sequence
of specifiers. Const expression is
another one as well. Anyway, that's
essentially how lambdas work. It's
pretty simple. I don't want to drag this
video on because
it it makes sense, I hope, to most
people. It is fairly simple. The usages
of it are the most important part. We're
going to look at one use for why you
might want to use a lambda in something
called STD find if, which is part of the
algorithm header file, and it's
basically something that we can use to
find a value inside of some kind of
iterator. So, over here we do have this
vector of values. I'm I've included
algorithm over here at the top, and then
I'm going to type in STD find if. So,
this function's basically just going to
accept some kind of iterator, so we'll
give it values begin and values end. So,
between the beginning and end of this
vector of values that we have here, we
can basically say, "Hey, return for me
an iterator that is the first element
that matches whatever kind of predicate
I pass in." So, in other words, what we
can do here is write a function that's
going to take in This is a vector of
integers, so we'll take an int value.
And then it has to return a boolean,
which basically says whether or not it
fulfills our condition. So, we'll say
maybe value is greater than three or
something like that. Let's just return
that. So, return value greater than
three. So, it's going to look through
this vector for numbers for integers
that are larger than three and return to
us an iterator of that, which will
essentially be just the first element.
So, what it should do, hopefully, is
return five for us. So, if we assign
this, auto iterator equals std::find_if,
um and then we'll print out
we'll dereference that iterator and
print it out, we should get the value
five printing. Why? Because we've
specified that we want a value greater
than three using a lambda,
and five happens to be the first number
that is greater than three inside this
list of values that we have. So, if I
just kind of put a breakpoint somewhere
here and run my code, you'll see that we
get the value five printing as we
expected. And we've managed to do that
fairly easily by just specifying a nice
little quick function that we want this
code this code to call. So, what this is
going to do is loop through our list,
kind of like what I've got here in for
each, and it's as if we just added a
little if value greater than five, then
return kind of that value. That's
basically what this is doing for us, but
we've we've we're able to specify this
if statement condition, this boolean, by
just using a lambda or the quick like
that. Anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed
this video. If you did, you can hit the
like button. That's pretty much all
there is to lambdas. Thank you huge
thank you as always to all of my Patreon
supporters. You can head on over to
patreon.com/thechannel
and help support all the videos that I
make here on my channel.
Next time, I don't even know what we're
going to what we're going to cover next
time, to be honest. Probably we haven't
even covered standard function yet, but
I feel like these function pointers are
just going to drag on for a while, and I
think you guys all understand them. If
you don't, definitely leave a comment
below.
But anyway,
I will see you guys next time. Goodbye.